you know what one of the things that
gives me a superpower if you will and
sort of itch as well is that we're gonna
say things that we think are true even
if you don't like them and we're not
gonna worry too much about what that
does to our career in my case you know
my career earnings when you know down
about 30 or 40 percent just by talking
about Trump I can't do speeches anymore
that was a huge part of my revenue I
can't do licensing anymore it would be
impossible to do a Dilbert movie if I
tried to do that today because would be
there would be too many people would say
hey that guy said something good about
Trump that one time now I've also said
lots of criticisms but but they don't
remember that they'll always see me as a
team so it's expensive and only the only
people can do it are the people who work
for themselves or find some way to
monetize the the danger right right and
if you can't monetize the danger which I
have learned to to some degree given my
experience with the boxing I mean I
don't know - they sent that you know but
I was totally doxxed I had a pen name
totally Docs my aunt Eva called me a
Nazi he got me fired from my job banned
from coaching Little League basically
stripped away my entire life and
identity my whole resume grad school
career everything up and smoked total
ashes you said your revenue went down
saw mine went to zero and completely
zero and I had this sort of jujitsu it
all into something productive and and I
have been able to do that but not the
people who are gonna be best at that
game aren't gonna aren't gonna sell out
so I wonder to what extent if you're all
or the independent sort of pirate outlaw
in the Bronze Age pervert lingo
continues to gather strength you know
power plays that's basically what
history is all about right the big big
power plays and struggle for power I
wonder how it plays out five to ten
years the interesting same well there's
like I said there's a new player in the
past you could be a really influential
person but if you didn't have a platform
nobody cared because you couldn't get
your message him or in the past you
might have a big platform but you didn't
know
the skill of persuasion you didn't know
it was something you could actually
learn and get better at but now you got
both so so it's almost like a warlord
situation where people are bringing you
know a million people with them on
whatever ride they want to take them and
if they're good at giving rides that the
numbers gonna grow
yeah fascinating yeah a warlord is a
very interesting language to use Bronze
Age pervert uses like outlaws and
pirates and he uses imagery of you know
like marauding pirates you know
traveling the globe taking over things
and it's all image or it's not it's not
that literal right yeah I like mine
better because the warlord assumes that
it's one person who's collected an army
yeah that and that's what social media
is more like you know these small armies
of people who have like like thoughts
did you read there was an article that
went around called the Internet of beefs
did you happen to read that that was
very popular recently no not it was very
very high quality very well done it made
the rounds and and it basically
described that we there's like sort of
knights crests and people rally around
the knight and and that it's basically
the Internet is a just a an arena for
conflict and then the people who follow
in the audience's you know they pick up
the banner of the the person that they
support and they sort of follow them all
around the internet supporting them and
going on the ride as as you described it
and what's interesting to me is you
don't need to have a million people
following you in order to have actual
real world influence you know I have
30,000 people which is nothing but more
importantly we have a hundred and fifty
guys in the liminal order which is our
sort of private community and it's there
where the real influence is happening
the real impacts happen because those
guys are actually changing their lives
and taking steps and measures that
impact themselves and their families and
their communities and that to me is sort
of boom the way that you build sort of a
long-term response to whatever cultural
problems you may see out there but it is
going to be interesting to see what
happens you know an environment full of
warlords
is in a steady state right like that
doesn't last forever or
or is it because like I said in my
earlier examples you know capitalism is
a bunch of robber barons and selfish
people they need jerks and you know
Crooks and Liars and yeah just the worst
people in the world but if your system
is built right it produces gold so I
don't know they're having all these
these warlords with different you know
idea sets I don't know that that's bad
because good ideas tend to win now if
I'm calling myself a warlord in this in
this context I don't mean it the bad way
because you know I wake up every day I
already made my money and tried to
contribute something to to society and I
work very hard and making sure that what
I do has a you know a real world you
know individual and collective benefit
and as we talked earlier a lot of my
ideas have bubbled up and become part of
society you know the the idea of talent
stacks the idea of systems being better
than goals those have always existed in
some form but by by capturing them in a
really digestible approachable
accessible form I was able to popularize
them in a way that maybe somebody who
didn't have persuasion and writing
skills could not have so that those are
two examples of ideas that go you know
they leave me and then they're there
fighting in the world of ideas and if
they win it's because they deserved it
yeah well those two ideas in particular
really had an influence on me and it
makes metalitz a king in particular
makes a the sort of innate desire i have
to keep learning things seem more
productive than it may have been before
and it also makes learning things which
seem to be inconsequential or manual or
slightly technical or detail makes them
all seem much more important too because
the more you continue to add as you know
to the stack the more opportunities you
have like for example for me I feel like
I'm rising out of the din of people on
social media because I actually have a
background that involves economics and
finance and public policy and I've run
companies and I've developed real estate
and I've written books I've done podcast
you just start to add them all up
together and then you have a unique
perspective that other people don't have
like I can't tell you the number of
times I've had to engage when I worked
in public policy I ran charter schools
so I ran charter schools for 10 years as
executive director but I came to it from
real estate perspective an
entrepreneurial background I just cannot
tell you the number of times that I
would be sitting there talking to people
who are running multi-million dollar
organizations that have absolutely no
idea how to run multiple organizations
because all they ever did was work in
education all they ever did was work in
education they just moved on to
education and all of a sudden they're
trying to run these businesses and they
really can't but the talent stacks made
it something a little bit more concrete
for me and it's also something that I
know a lot of guys are really grabbing
on to and just continuing to enhance and
and further its sort of the being an
autodidact and teaching yourself and
expanding your capabilities and
eventually they all just line up and
cross up into something that becomes
unique and and in this world and in this
information environment being unique is
is key and also key is getting
discovered I was having this
conversation the other day and people
ask me all the time how can I get to
where you are or how can I write or how
can I do this and and I tell them like
being discovered is the hardest part
everybody has a platform now but you can
even have great content but getting
discovered is very difficult and I
explained my idea was you have to be
sort of high variance in order to get
discovered what do you think about that
what advice would you give to somebody
who's got talent and a platform but
nobody's listening well I'm gonna gonna
give you an opposing viewpoint here yes
I once asked a table full of high-end
publishers and editors so some of the
best in New York City the the high-end
publishing company and I asked this
question of all the people there
collectively they probably had several
hundreds of years of experience
publishing and I said do there exist
great writers
who can't get published and every one of
them said at the same time
no doesn't exist because and and this is
something that that I've discovered you
know anecdotally through my own life
that there is so much hunger for a good
content that if you produce it your odds
of finding a place for or you closer to
100% than zero and I have an implication
of your statement as pretty much well
hold on yeah hold on now it doesn't but
it doesn't mean it happens right away
all right so certainly it takes a little
bit of luck just like everything else
but I'll give you some concrete examples
it was at a co-worker back when I worked
in my cubicle forum at Pacific Valley we
decided to write a book had never
written the book you know didn't have
any background that was suggests he
could but he saw me write a book and he
thought well if this guy could write a
book how hard is it to write a book so
he just he sets the site on writing a
book comes up with this great story you
know it doesn't matter what it is gets
published and they asked him to write
another book now of course they edited
all of his writing to you know fix it
and everything but they they liked his
idea and Stephen King has a book called
on writing the Nao's recommend and what
he recommends is that you start writing
for anybody who will you know take it
and that gives you a little bit of a
resume for the you know the the the
person it doesn't pay much but they're
hungry for content and then that gives
you another resume to ratchet up very
good advice but it but basically if you
can create content that people want the
the market is actually surprisingly easy
to get published at least now to your
example is here but you're biting your
tongue here because it would suggest
that you know you're thinking well why
don't I have a million followers already
because like I content is great people
tell me or I wasn't thinking about me
I'm fine but but but you in fact are
succeeding so you're so I would say that
the evidence suggests that your content
is excellent because the evidence yeah
you got me on your show
you got you got 30,000 people following
you on Twitter and these things were
likely to increase so I feel that and
and by the way cartooning let me tell
you how hard it was to become a
cartoonist I think at least at the time
2,000 people or so would try to submit
comics to become syndicated cartoonist
meaning being in newspapers and Ana
there was 2000 they might pick five and
they would work with them for a year and
maybe only one or two of them they'll
decide to go go ahead with so you'd say
to yourself well the odds of becoming a
cartoonist they're just so bad it's like
you know one in 500 one in a thousand
but then you talk to the editor who
asked to pick cartoonists and you say
how many of those two thousand are
actually good and you find out well a
thousand of them come from the elderly
and people in prison I'm not even making
that up maybe even right and then you
know there's another several hundred of
them that don't have any talent at all
and those can be rejected in moments so
finding anybody who could actually do
the work of being a cartoonist is so
unusual that if you can do it you're
probably going to be a cartoonist and
you're probably going to get paid for it
so if you have talent people are gonna
find you if you don't have talent that's
the problem but but but if you do have
talent you're still gonna have to put
yourself out there right you're gonna
have to get noticed right okay so my
discoverability notion is a little bit
still in play but you're saying that
that talent will rise and if you're
consistent and you take what I think you
wrote about you call them micro steps
that you will then be able to stack up
some success and and I think that I have
found that to be true too
you know when I first started out nobody
was listening
nobody not anybody you know I would
write a blog post and I'd be happy if I
got 25 views on it I didn't even know
how many of those were just you know
BOTS or crawlers or whatever and you
know now I can be pretty sure that like
thousands of people are gonna see it and
thousands of people buy the book and
come see me speak and whatever so it's
it's very interesting to see it all
happen and I love to see your
description of the system which you also
just referenced with Stephen King in
micro steps and so that's something that
I try to get my guys to do and I know
there's a lot of people in sort of the
self-help Twitter world that will say
and hammer you over the head is just get
started all right just get started make
some mistakes I think I just read in
your book that you know you do it you
make mistakes you get the most valuable
feedback you're gonna get people will
tell you exactly exactly what's wrong
with it
the the biggest difference between a
professional writer who's getting paid
for their work and someone who wants to
be a professional writer is that the
professional writer who does get paid
wrote stuff that's the biggest
difference yeah I can't tell you how
many people want to be an author but
they don't write anything if you're not
if you're not writing anything you're
not really moving in that direction
right right yeah and so in a realistic
world today I mean if you want to be a
writer you could start you know
obviously you start your own blog you
could then submit there's a million
websites that are looking for content
probably free at that point at that
point and you're right you just keep
building it over time so but there's one
other element that's right time time is
that other element there how do you how
would you suggest people you know find
the strength or the the stamina to keep
going until that moment that to turn
that was those ten years into an
overnight success as it were well a
couple of things and I would agree with
Stephen King here I think he recommends
that you keep your day job while you're
while you're doing this other thing so
you don't want to be starving while
you're getting your other thing off the
ground but one of the things I
discovered that seems to be just a
universal truth is they're things which
will eventually work whether it's a
product or your writing or something
things that will eventually work work
right away and they work in a terrible
form and I'll give you some example
do you remember the first cellphones
they're like this big brick and you
dropped your calls and it was expensive
basically everything that could be wrong
with the product was wrong with the
first cell phones but people wanted them
faster than they could be built so that
told you that that was going to be huge
the first computers were just a mess
they were crashing they were slow they
needed floppy disks but everybody wanted
them and you could tell that that wasn't
gonna stop so and in Dilbert - when
Dilbert was first published even though
it was a failure for the first several
years because didn't grow an audience
the audience that it did get were just
over the over the moon so it had a very
intense cult following which I said AHA
you don't get that unless there's
something there
so I still had to improve my talent to
take it to the next level I was very bad
when I first started because didn't have
practice being a cartoonist but once I
had done it for a while
I just ratcheted up the quality and
eventually it caught on I mean it takes
a little luck and you have to hang
around a while but people found me
yeah I guess if the moment for me where
I realized that I could actually do make
something of the writing is when people
that didn't know me who weren't my mom
and weren't my girlfriend and weren't my
friends were like oh I read this is
really good oh man somebody who had no
invested interest in their opinion and
it wasn't gonna impact me in any way or
at least that their opinion was gonna
impact them came out with something
positive and that you know for somebody
that's in a wanting to develop a
creative career and to move forward that
those little pieces little pieces of
gold you really got to hang on to them
it's like a little Fleck and they just
hang on to it in your palm of your hand
and you get one more like yeah one more
Fleck and you add it up and before you
know it things start taking off and I
think that that's best sort of where
where I am right now I've finally
accepted finally because you know I have
issues like a lot of people where you
just can't even believe good things that
are happening like it's so much easier
to believe the bad things that are
to you then the good things but I
finally come to the point I think now
where I feel confident that I can put
out good content and people are into it
but in your case you said that it you
Dilbert was a failure for the first
couple of years now that's an
interesting statement because I think a
lot of people would say oh it was a
syndicated cartoon that sounds like
success you're getting paid right you're
getting paid probably every time it gets
published and so a lot of people that
scream success but to you that said
failure how was that failure so I don't
know the exact number but something like
405 comics they get launched don't ever
pick up an audience and then they just
slowly go away and get cancelled so I
was in fewer than a hundred newspapers
and they weren't the big ones the big
ones pay more than the small ones so it
wasn't enough to earn a living I had to
keep my day job and it wasn't growing so
the the sales team they they will sell
it when it's new but if it doesn't sell
on its own after that they they just
move on to the next thing to try to get
a hit because it's sort of sort of about
hits right it's not about the average
cartoon so once my cycle had ended and
they weren't selling it actively and it
was just the number of newspapers that
were just cancelling and nobody was
buying I looked for something to get
attention and I started putting my email
address in the panel of this trip
thousands of people would write to me
every day because they didn't have and
they would say we like it when Dilbert's
in the office doing work stuff we don't
like it when he's at home and at the
time he was always at home and only
rarely in the office so I said well my
background is not art my background is
economics and Business School and I just
heard thousands of my customers ask for
the same thing all right if you could
have a better indicator of something
that's going to work it's all of your
customers spontaneously asked for an
identical thing yeah and then so because
I'm not an artist so I don't have the
you know they are you sure are you sure
you can still say that's got
well not none the not in the sense of
artistic integrity meaning that I look
at my work as I guess I I degrade the
quality of my own work to say it's not
special it's a product people like my
product or they don't like my product
but it's just a product yeah it's not
like some amazing part of my body or
something so you know I I just took the
business persons approach and said well
if that's what they want I'll make it a
business cartoon and that immediately
allowed people to talk about it as the
business cartoon it became the the face
of downsizing in the 90s it became the
you know the face of the dot-com thing
so just lots of things happened after
that one change